New York County Psychiatric Society Records Finding Aid
Oskar Diethelm Library
New York County Psychiatric Society Records
1927 - 1990
This collection contains records from the New York County Psychiatric Society. The collection has 6 series: Constitution, Programs, and Reports on History of the District Branch; Correspondence; Committees; Executive Council Minutes; Assembly of District Branches; and Publications.
2.92 linear feet (7 boxes)
New York County Psychiatric Society
Oskar Diethelm Library DeWitt Wallace Institute of Psychiatry: History, Policy and the Arts Weill Cornell Medical College 525 East 68th Street, Box 140 New York, NY 10065
1973.0001
Gift of New York County Psychiatric Society, 1973.
Box 2, Series III, folder 4 is restricted from use to protect the identity of individuals mentioned.
The New York County Psychiatric Society was founded in 1922 as the New York Society for Clinical Psychiatry and became an affiliate society of the American Psychiatric Association in 1947. It was known as the New York County District Branch from 1952-1958 and thereafter was designated as the New York Society for Clinical Psychiatry, New York County Branch, American Psychiatric Association, and the New York County District Branch-American Psychiatric Association. According to its constitution, it was organized for educational and scientific purposes and engages in activities to advance the art and science of the psychiatric field. Activities are focused on the continuing psychiatric education of the membership. The District Branch functions as a component of the American Psychiatric Association and fulfills the objectives, functions, and activities of the APA.
New York County Psychiatric Society; American Psychiatric Association
This collection contains records from the New York County Psychiatric Society. There are 6 series in this collection.
Constitution, Programs, and Reports on History of the District Branch: Copies of the Constitution, bylaws, and meeting programs are housed in this series. Dr. Marie-Louise Schoelly’s report written for the 50th anniversary of the founding of the District Branch provides information on changes that have occurred over the years.
Correspondence: This is primarily from the office of the Secretary-Treasurer, Dr. Sidney Malitz. The correspondence relates to the general operation of the District Branch. There are also official letters written by the president and distributed to the entire membership. These are followed by lists of names of the presidents-elects and presidents. Because there are so few financial records, official accounting financial reports are included in this series.
Committees: Numerous committees comprise the District Branch, however only a few are represented in this collection There are many versions of the constitution and bylaws during the period of revision (1962-1964). The Ethics Committee material (Folder 2:4) is restricted to protect the identity of individuals mentioned therein.
Executive Council Minutes: The Executive Council recommends the admission or rejection of applicants to the District Branch and disciplinary measures relative to members; appoints and sets salaries of such personnel as auditors, accountants, and attorneys; adopts a budget and controls the funds; approves publication of its proceedings and other papers; and considers proposed amendments to the constitution and bylaws. The Executive Council is composed of the four officers of the District Branch, the two immediate Past-Presidents, and seven voting members.
Assembly of District Branches: This body is composed of approximately 75 district branches of the APA across the country. The Assembly was designed to provide a greater voice in the governance of the national organization. The Council of the New York State District Branches represented the State in the Assembly of District Branches. The Committee of Delegates consisted of 11 district branches in New York City and was a loose confederation. Later the organization changed and was based on a more formal structure. The Council of Delegates was a confederation of district branches in New York State.
Publications: This series consists primarily of newsletters published by the District Branch. Two membership directories and a few reports prepared by other organizations are included.
- Constitution, Programs, and Reports on History of the District Branch
  - Constitution and bylaws, 1942 - 1985 (Box 1)
  - Annual meeting programs and lists of members, 1927 - 1959 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, reports, and related material pertaining to the history and growth of the District Branch, Undated (Box 1)
  - “The New York Society for Clinical Psychiatry is Fifty Years Old" paper by Marie-Louise Schoelly, 1972 (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  - General correspondence, 1963 (Box 1)
  - General correspondence, 1964 (Box 1)
  - General correspondence, 1965 (Box 1)
  - General correspondence, 1966 (Box 1)
  - General correspondence, 1967 (Box 1)
  - General correspondence, 1968 (Box 1)
  - General correspondence, 1969 (Box 1)
  - General correspondence, 1970 (Box 1)
  - General correspondence, 1970 (Box 1)
  - General correspondence, 1971 (Box 1)
  - President’s Letters, Abraham N. Franzblau, 1971 - 1972 (Box 1)
  - List of presidents-elect, District Branches, 1963 (Box 1)
  - List of APA Committee Liaison Committee members to the District Branches and District Branch presidents, 1966 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence on finances, statements of income and expenses, 1963 - 1967 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence, statements, programs, 1970 - 1972 (Box 1)
- Committees
  - Financial reports, 1962 - 1967 (Box 2)
  - Financial reports, 1968 - 1972 (Box 2)
  - Committee on Constitution, 1964 - 1973 (Box 2)
  - Ethics Committee RESTRICTED, 1972 (Box 2)
  - Committee on History of Psychiatry, 1962 - 1970 (Box 2)
  - Committee on Hospital Psychiatry, Directory of In-Patient Psychiatric Services in Metropolitan New York, 1970 - 1971 (Box 2)
  - Ad Hoc Committee on New York Regional Office, 1965 (Box 2)
  - Nominating Committee, 1988 (Box 2)
  - Committee on Psychiatric Acute Care, Directory of Psychiatric Acute Care Services in New York and Richmond Counties, 1971 - 1972 (Box 2)
  - Committee on Revision of Constitution and Bylaws, 1962 (Box 2)
  - Committee on Revision of Constitution and Bylaws, 1964 (Box 2)
  - Committee on Revision of Constitution and Bylaws, 1963 - 1964 (Box 2)
  - Lists of committees and their members, 1953 - 1972 (Box 2)
- Executive Council Minutes
  - Minutes, 1960 (Box 3)
  - Minutes, 1961 (Box 3)
  - Minutes, 1962 (Box 3)
  - Minutes, 1963 (Box 3)
  - Minutes, 1964 (Box 3)
  - Minutes, 1965 (Box 3)
  - Minutes, 1966 (Box 3)
  - Minutes, 1967 (Box 3)
  - Minutes, 1968 (Box 3)
  - Minutes, 1969 (Box 3)
  - Minutes, 1969 (Box 3)
  - Minutes, 1970 (Box 3)
  - Minutes, 1971 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence and reports, 1971 (Box 4)
  - Minutes, Code of Procedure, 1972 (Box 4)
  - Reports, 1972 (Box 4)
  - Minutes, 1973 (Box 4)
  - Minutes, 1974 (Box 4)
- Assembly of District Branches
  - New York State District Branches, transactions of the Committee of Delegates, 1960 (Box 4)
  - New York State District Branches, transactions of the Committee of Delegates, 1962 (Box 4)
  - New York State District Branches, transactions of the Committee of Delegates, 1963 (Box 4)
  - Council of New York State Branches, transactions of the Committee of Delegates, 1964 (Box 4)
  - Council of New York State Branches transactions, 1965 (Box 4)
  - Council of New York State Branches transactions, 1966 (Box 4)
  - Council of New York State Branches transactions, 1967 (Box 4)
  - Minutes, 1961 (Box 5)
  - Minutes, 1962 (Box 5)
  - Minutes, 1963 (Box 5)
  - Minutes, 1964 (Box 5)
  - Minutes, 1965 (Box 5)
  - Minutes, 1966 (Box 5)
  - Minutes, 1967 (Box 5)
  - Minutes, 1967 (Box 5)
  - Minutes, reports, 1968 (Box 5)
  - Minutes, 1968 (Box 5)
  - Minutes, 1969 (Box 6)
  - List of officers, board of trustees, members of councils, committees, etc., 1969 (Box 6)
  - Minutes, Procedural Code, 1969 (Box 6)
  - Minutes, 1970 (Box 6)
  - Minutes, 1970 (Box 6)
  - Minutes, 1971 (Box 6)
  - Minutes, 1971 (Box 6)
  - Minutes, Procedural Code, 1972 (Box 6)
  - Minutes, 1972 (Box 6)
- Publications
  - Newsletters, 1981 - 1984 (Box 7)
  - Newsletters, 1985 - 1988 (Box 7)
  - Membership directories, 1970 - 1973 (Box 7)
  - Reports by other organizations on ethics, community mental health centers, 1972 (Box 7)
  - Announcements of meetings, 1989 - 1990 (Box 7)